Finding Aid for Department of Aerospace Engineering (University of Michigan) publications
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Department of Aerospace Engineering (University of Michigan) publications 1963-1994
University of Michigan. Department of Aerospace Engineering.
0.5 linear feet
9714; Bimu; C146; 2
Contains brochures and pamphlets, bulletins, newsletters, building prospectuses, and reports, including the report of the review committee. Also includes golden anniversary convocation addresses The Next Fifty Years in Aviation and Astronautics -- Past and Present. Also contains an anecdotal history entitled The First Fifty Years (A Fragmentary Anecdotal History).
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The publications are received periodically from the unit (donor no. 2320) and the College of Engineering (donor no. 1884 ).
The publications are open for research use.
Periodic additions to the records expected.
The Department of Aeronautical Engineering was established in 1916 and the first degree awarded in 1917. Professor Felix W. Pawlowski, who had taken the first aeronautical engineering course ever offered, that of at Marchis in Paris, was hired by Dean Cooley as instructor of Mechanical Engineering in 1914 and began lecturing on aeronautics. The separate degree program established in 1916 was the first in the United States.
The Department of Aerospace Engineering Publications (.5 linear feet) are divided into four series: Unit Publications, Sub-Unit Publications, Topical Publications, and Student Publications. The bulk of the publications document the Department of Aerospace Engineering and its sub-units.
The Unit Publications series contains printed material published specifically by the Department of Aerospace Engineering. These publications are defined as being widely distributed and may be published at regular intervals. They are arranged by genre of the publication.
The Unit Publications series includes brochures, bulletins describing the graduate programs, newsletters, prospectuses and reports. The Bentley Historical Library holds the Alumni Newsletter from 1989 to 1994. There is a prospectus, published in 1988, for the Francois-Xavier Bagnoud Building entitled Prospectus for a New Building for the Department of Aerospace Engineering. There is also a report from the department Review Committee published in 1988.
The Sub-Unit Publications series contains publications from subordinate offices, departments, programs and organizations within the Department of Aerospace Engineering. These publications are arranged alphabetically by the creating sub-unit. The Sub-Unit Publications include brochures, case statements, programs, from the Aerodynamics for Industry Program, Aeronautical Design Symposium, Aerospace Engineering Complex, and the Aerospace System Design Team. Under the heading “Development” publications such as lectures from the Francois-Xavier Bagnoud Aerospace Prize and brochures and programs describing the Francois-Xavier Bagnoud building are found. There is a newsletter, published in 1991, from the Michigan Space Grant Consortium. The annual report published in 1982 describes the activities for the Self-Contained Orbital Research Experiment (SCORE) from the Senior Design Class.
The Topical Publications series includes printed materials published to document specific events or activities such as celebrations or one-time conferences hosted by the Department of Aerospace Engineering. The Topical Publications series includes printed material from the Golden Anniversary celebration which took place in 1964. It includes an article entitled Space Research at the University published in 1963, convocation addresses, a brief history of the first fifty years of aerospace engineering at the University of Michigan, and programs.
The Student Publications series contains publications published by student groups within the Department of Aerospace Engineering. The Student Publications series includes flyers from the American Institute of Aeronautics and Astronautics.
Subjects:
University of Michigan. Dept. of Aerospace Engineering.; Pamphlets.; Bulletins.; Prospectuses.; Reports.; Histories.; Newsletters.; Next fifty years in aviation.
- Unit Publications
  - Brochures 1969-1994 (Box 1)
  - Bulletins
    - Aerospace Engineering at the University of Michigan, circa 1989 (Box 1)
    - Graduate Degree Programs in Aerospace Engineering, undated (Box 1)
  - Newsletters
    - Alumni Newsletter, 1989-1994, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Programs 2000 (Box 1)
  - Prospectus
    - Prospectus for a New Building for the Department of Aerospace Engineering, 1988 (Box 1)
  - Reports
    - Report of the Review Committee, 1988 (Box 1)
- Sub-Unit Publications
  - Aerodynamics for Industry Program
    - Brochures undated (Box 1)
  - Aeronautical Design Symposium
    - Programs 1989 (Box 1)
  - Aerospace Engineering Complex
    - Case Statements 1987 (Box 1)
  - Aerospace System Design Team
    - Project Lustar: Lunar Space Transport with Aeroassisted Return, 1985 (Box 1)
  - Development
    - Francois-Xavier Bagnoud Aerospace Prize
      - Lectures 1993 (Box 1)
    - Francois-Xavier Bagnoud Building
      - Brochures 1989 (Box 1)
      - Programs 1989, 1993 (Box 1)
  - Michigan Space Grant Consortium
    - Newsletters
      - Newsletter, 1991 (Box 1)
  - Senior Design Class
    - Self Contained Orbital Research Experiment (SCORE)
      - Annual Reports 1982 (Box 1)
- Topical Publications
  - Golden Anniversary Celebration 1964
    - Articles
      - Space Research at the University, 1963 (Box 1)
    - Convocation Addresses
      - The Next Fifty Years in Aviation, 1964 (Box 1)
      - Astronautics--Past and Future, 1964 (Box 1)
    - Histories
      - The First Fifty Years (A Fragmentary, Anecdotal History) 1964 (Box 1)
    - Programs 1964 (Box 1)
- Student Organizations
  - American Institute of Aeronautics and Astronautics
    - Flyers 1982 (Box 1)